Register of the Gerua Collection, 1906-1920
Hoover Institution Archives
Gerua Collection,
1906-1920
25003
Gerua, Boris Vladimirovich, 1876-1942
11 manuscript boxes. (4.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, communiques, and printed matter, relating to White Russian military activities in northern Russia during the Russian Revolution, and to White Russian liaison with the British War Office. Consists mainly of records of the White Russian special military mission to Great Britain from 1919 to 1920. Includes some papers of Boris V. Gerua, head of the mission.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Yudenich, Nikolay Nikolayevich, 1862-1933.; Russia (Territory under White armies, 1918-1920) Armiia.; Great Britain.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--History--Allied intervention, 1918-1920.; Russia. Armiia--Officers.
Historical Note
The Spetsial'naia Voennaia Missiia Shtaba Verhkovnago Glavnokomanduiushchago v Londone (Special Military Mission of the Staff of the Supreme Commander-in-Chief in London) was established in 1919 by Gen. Nikolai IUdenich under the direction Major-Gen. Boris Gerua (Heroys). The purpose of the mission was to obtain from the British government financial support,supplies, transportation and equipment for Russian troops joining the Army of the North-West. The mission was dissolved in 1920.
Biographical Note
1876 Born, St. Petersburg
1904 Graduates Pazheskii Korpus and Nikolaevskaia Akademiia General'nago Shtaba
1904-1905 Participates in the Russo-Japanese War
1912 Appointed professor of tactics at the Nikolaevskaia Akademiia General'nago Shtaba
1914 Fights on the Galician Front
1915 Appointed commander of the Leib-gvardii Izmailovskii Polk
1917 May Appointed Chief of Staff of the 11th Army
1917 August Arrested on orders of Kerensky for participation in the Kornilov affair
1918 Escapes to Finland and is sent to Great Britain by Gen. Nikolai IUdenich as head of the Spetsial'naia Voennaia Missiia Shtaba Verhkovnago Glavnokomanduiushchago v Londone
1920 After the liquidation of the mission, continues to reside in Great Britain. Takes part in emigré organizations, publishes memoirs and other works, continues his artistic activities and interests
1942 Dies, Coulton-St. Mary, Devon, England
Scope and Content Note
The collection includes an extensive correspondence between various White Russian offices and officials, especially related to military operations on the North-Western and Petrograd fronts. Copies of this correspondence sent to the mission are to be found in the OFFICE FILE series. It also includes numerous reports on the political situation in Europe especially as related to the White Russsian cause, found in the OFFICE and PRESS FILE series.
Series Description
- BORIS VLADIMIROVICH GERUA FILE, 1919-1920. (Box No. 1.)
  Official correspondence under his signature as head of the Spetsial'naia Voennaia Missiia Shtaba Verhkovnago Glavnokomanduiushchago v Londone, personal correspondence and a report re his personal experiences in the Soviet Union, arranged by physical form and therein chronologically
- OFFICE FILE, 1919-1920. (Box No. 2.-4.)
  Correspondence both of the Spetsial'naia Voennaia Missiia Shtaba Verhkovnago Glavnokomanduiushchago v Londone and copies of correspondence received by the mission from other offices and officials of the White governments, material related to relations with the British government, reports re the political situation in various European countries especially as related to the position of Russian refugees and the Russian Armies, arranged by physical form and therein alphabetically
- FINANCIAL RECORDS FILE, 1919-1920. (Box No. 5.)
  Correspondence related to efforts by the Spetsial'naia Voennaia Missiia Shtaba Verhkovnago Glavnokomanduiushchago v Londone to receive financial aid and supplies from the British government for Gen. Nikolai IUdenich's Army of the North-West, and includes financial papers related to the financing of the London office, arranged by subject and therein by physical form
- MILITARY OPERATIONS FILE, 1919-1920. (Box No. 5.-6.)
  Dispatches and telegrams re troop movements, maps, orders, operational reports and Soviet and Russian wireles reports transcribed by the British War Office, arranged by physical form and therein by subject
- MILITARY PERSONNEL FILE, 1919-1920. (Box No. 6.-7.)
  Material related to the recruitment of personnel for the White armies, and especially IUdenich's Army of the North-West. Includes reports re Russian prisoners of war, applications of Russian and foreign volunteers, and correspondence re transfer and supply of troops
- PRESS FILE, 1919-1920. (Box No. 7.-8.)
  Clippings and single issues of newspapers, pamphlets, summaries and excerpts from the foreign press related to the White cause, arranged by physical form and therein by subject
- SUPPLY FILE, 1919-1920. (Box No. 8.-9.)
  Correspondence related to the problem of supplying the Army of the North-West, arranged by physical form and therein by subject
- SUBJECT FILE, 1906-1920. (Box No. 9.-11.)
  Printed matter related to the election laws and elections to the the Russian Duma, 1906-1917, and to reform in local government proposed by the Ministerstvo Vnutrennikh Del, 1917, and miscellaneous material related to various emigré political organizations, arranged by subject
Container List
- BORIS VLADIMIROVICH GERUA FILE, 1919-1920
  - Correspondence (Box 1.)
    - Official
      - Incoming, 1919
        - General
          - Undated-August (Folder 1)
          - September-October (Folder 2)
          - November-December (Folder 3)
        - Iudenich, Nikolai (Folder 4)
      - Outgoing
        - General
          - 1919
            - Undated-May (Folder 5)
            - July (Folder 6)
            - August (Folder 7)
            - September-October (Folder 8)
            - November-December (Folder 9)
          - 1920 (Folder 10)
        - Churchill, Winston (Folder 11)
        - IUdenich, Nikolai, 1919. Includes reports
          - Undated-August (Folder 12)
          - September-December (Folder 13)
    - Personal. Incoming
      - Unidated-April 1919 (Folder 14)
      - May 1919-1920 (Folder 15)
    - Miscellany. Includes drafts, unidentified writings and personal papers (Folder 16-17)
  - Reports
    - General. Includes caricatures of Russian political figures (Folder 18)
    - Personal experiences in the Soviet Union (Folder 19)
- OFFICE FILE, 1919-1920.
  Spetsial'naia Voennaia Missiia Shtaba Verhkovnago Glavnokomanduiushchago v Londone
  - Agreement between the ARA and the Provisional Government of Russia, 1919 July (Box 2., Folder 1)
  - Correspondence. Includes both correspondence of the Spetsial'naia Missiia and copies of correspondence of other Provisional Government offices and officials
    - General. Incoming telegrams, arranged by city of origin
      - Arkhangel'sk (Folder 2)
      - Athens (Folder 3)
      - Belgrade (Folder 4)
      - Berlin (Folder 5)
      - Constantinople (Folder 6)
      - Copenhagen. Includes correspondence of Sergei Pototskii (Folder 7)
      - Ekaterinodar (Folder 8)
      - Hague (Folder 9)
      - Helsingfors (Helsinki) (Folder 10)
      - London
        - General (Folder 11)
        - Golovin, Nikolai (Folder 12)
        - Kholmnsen, Ivan (Folder 13)
      - Malta (Folder 14)
      - Omsk
        - General (Folder 15)
        - Sukin, Ivan to Sergei Sazonov (Folder 16)
      - Paris
        - Undated (Folder 17)
        - January-April (Folder 18)
        - May-June (Folder 19)
        - July (Folder 20)
        - August-November (Folder 21)
      - Prague (Folder 22)
      - Revel (Folder 23)
      - Rome (Folder 24)
      - Stockholm. Includes correspondence of Dmitrii Kandaurov
        - January-April (Folder 25)
        - May (Folder 26)
        - June-July (Folder 27)
        - August-December (Folder 28)
      - Taganrog (Folder 29)
      - Teheran (Folder 30)
      - Tokyo (Folder 31)
      - Washington (Folder 32)
    - American Mission in Paris (Folder 33)
    - Cowan, Walter to Nikolai IUdenich (Folder 34)
    - Gardner, Daniel (Box 3.)
      - Incoming (Folder 1)
      - Outgoing. Includes reports (Folder 2)
    - Gough, Hubert to Nikolai IUdenich (Folder 3)
    - Great Britain
      - General. Translations of memoranda, reports and correspondence made available to the British government by Russian representatives in London
        - Undated-May (Folder 4)
        - June-November (Folder 5)
      - War Office
        - Incoming
          - March-August (Folder 6)
          - September-October (Folder 7)
          - November-December (Folder 8)
        - Outgoing
          - Undated-August (Folder 9)
          - September-October (Folder 10)
          - November-December (Folder 11)
    - Guchkov, Aleksandr. Includes letter to Winston Churchill (Folder 12)
    - IUdenich, Nikolai
      - Incoming (Folder 13)
      - Outgoing
        - General (Folder 14)
        - Churchill, Winston, 1920 January (Folder 15)
  - Journals of correspondence
    - Incoming (Folder 16-17)
    - Outgoing (Folder 18)
  - Official orders of Russian government establishing the special military mission in Great Britain (Box 4., Folder 1)
  - Personnel file (Folder 2)
  - Publicity and propaganda file (Folder 3)
  - Record of material received
    - Encoded telegrams (Folder 4)
    - Secret documents (Folder 5)
  - Reports
    - General (Folder 6)
    - Baltic region (Folder 7-8)
    - Denmark (Folder 9)
    - Estonia (Folder 10)
    - Finland (Folder 11-12)
    - Germany (Folder 13)
    - Italy (Folder 14)
    - Latvia (Folder 15)
    - Lithuania (Folder 16)
    - Poland (Folder 17)
    - Soviet Union (Folder 18)
    - Sweden (Folder 19)
    - Ukraine (Folder 20)
    - United States (Folder 21)
- FINANCIAL RECORDS FILE, 1919-1920
  - General (Box 5.)
    - Correspondence
      - General (Folder 1)
      - Gerua, Boris
        - Incoming (Folder 2)
        - Outgoing (Folder 3)
      - IUdenich, Nikolai (Folder 4)
    - List of correspondence (Folder 5)
    - Receipts and disbursements (Folder 6)
  - Financing of London office
    - General (Folder 7)
    - Disbursements. Notebooks (Folder 8)
    - Receipts (Folder 9)
- MILITARY OPERATIONS FILE, 1919-1920
  - Dispatches, situation reports and telegrams re troop movements and military operations (Box 5.)
    - General (Folder 10)
    - Arkhangel'sk front (Folder 11)
    - North-Western front and Petrograd region (Folder 12)
    - Siberian front (Folder 13)
    - Southern front (Folder 14)
  - Maps (Folder 15-16)
  - Orders - Army of the North-West (Folder 17)
  - Reports
    - General
      - General (Folder 18)
      - Soviet Union
        - Army - Strategic position and strength on various fronts (Folder 19)
        - Navy (Folder 20)
    - Operational reports (by military fronts) (Box 6.)
      - General (Folder 1)
      - North-West (Folder 2-3)
      - Petrograd
        - Condition of civilian population (Folder 4)
        - Strategic situation (Folder 5)
      - South Russia. Includes some correspondence (Folder 6)
    - Wireless radio reports transcribed and translated by the British War Office
      - Moscow. Field headquarters of the Revolutionary Military Soviet of the Republic
        - No. 3-884 (Folder 7)
        - No. 2533-2789 (Folder 8)
        - No. 2815-3063 (Folder 9)
      - Nikolaev. Headquarters of the Commander-in-Chief of the Armed Forces in South Russia (Folder 10-11)
      - Riga (Folder 12)
- MILITARY PERSONNEL FILE, 1919-1920.
  Material relating to the recruitment of personnel for White Armies. Includes material re officers of the Russian Imperial Army and White Army abroad and their transfer to active duty as well as enlistment of former Russian prisoners of war
  - General. Correspondence (Box 6.)
    - General
      - Unitdate-September 1919 (Folder 13)
      - October 1919-January 1920 (Folder 14)
    - Gerua, Boris (Folder 15)
  - Individual applications. Includes that of Arkadii Borman (Folder 16-17)
  - Recruitment of military personnel (Box 7.)
    - General. Correspondence and reports re Russian officers abroad and former prisoners of war
      - General (Folder 1-2)
      - Newmarket Camp (Folder 3)
    - Foreigners
      - General
        - General. Includes contract document for foreign volunteers (Folder 4)
        - British volunteers. Includes list of British personnel with Russian Detachment (Folder 5)
      - Belosel'skii-Belozerskii, Sergei. Miscellaneous material related to his recruiting activities (Folder 6)
  - Supply and organization of military units (Folder 7)
  - Transfer of troops from the Army of IUdenich to the Army of the South, December 1919-March 1920 (Folder 8)
- PRESS FILE, 1919-1920
  - Bulletins. "Union", Bureau de la Presse Russe (Box 7., Folder 9)
  - Newspaper file
    - General
      - La cause commune, 1919 July and 1920 March (Folder 10)
      - Russkaia Zhizn', 1919 May-July (Folder 11)
      - Russkoe Delo, 1919 April (Folder 12)
      - Severnaia Zhizn', 1919 January (Folder 13)
    - Clippings
      - British (Folder 14)
      - French (Folder 15)
  - Summaries and excerpts from foreign press (Box 8.)
    - Great Britain (Folder 1)
    - Estonia (Folder 2)
    - Denmark (Folder 3-6)
    - Finland (Folder 7)
    - France (Folder 8)
    - Soviet Union (Folder 9)
    - Sweden. Includes Russkii Kurier (Folder 10)
  - Pamphlets
    - Kratkaia zapiska o vozniknovenii Severnago Korpusa I dal'neishei ego boevoi deiatel'nosti, 1918 November (Folder 11)
    - The German-Bolshevik Conspiracy, The Committee on Public Information, 1918 October (Folder 12)
    - Golos vserossiiskoi vlasti, Helsingfors, 1919 (Folder 13)
    - The Russian Commonwealth, 1919 April (Folder 14)
    - Zemlia--Daiushchim Khleb, Moscow, 1919 June (Folder 15)
- SUPPLY FILE, 1919-1920
  - Correspondence (Box 8.)
    - General, 1919
      - Undated-August (Folder 16)
      - September-October (Folder 17)
      - November-December (Folder 18)
    - British War Office. See OFFICE FILE, Correspondence
    - Commercial supply firms (Folder 19)
    - Gardner, Daniel. See OFFICE FILE, Correspondence
  - Reports (Box 9.)
    - General
      - General (Folder 1)
      - Supply of occupied territories and Petrograd (Folder 2)
    - Supplies
      - Received (Folder 3-4)
      - Requested (Folder 5)
  - Transportation file - Olga (ship) (Folder 6)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1906-1920
  - Conférence Politique Russe, 1919 March. Letter under signature of S. Sazonov et al. to Peace Conference (Box 9., Folder 7)
  - Kornilov, Lavr. Report, "Glumlenie bol'shevikov nad telom ubitago generala Kornilova" (Folder 8)
  - Ligue Française de l'Enseignement. Speech by Boris Savinkov (Folder 9)
  - Rossiiskoe Obshchestvo Krasnago Kresta. Miscellany (Folder 10)
  - Russia
    - Gosudarstvennaia Duma, 1906-1917. Includes, "Proekt polozheniia o vyborakh v Uchreditel'noe Sobranie", "Polozhenie o vyborakh v Gosudarstvennuiu Dumu", "Stat'i proekta postanovleniia vremennago pravitel'stva o vyborakh v Uchreditel'noe Sobranie" and other documents related to election laws and the election process in Russia (Folder 11-18)
    - Gosudarstvennaia Duma, 1906-1917 (Box 10., Folder 1-4)
    - Ministerstvo Vnutrennikh Del, 1917 April 13-November 7, "Spravochnyi listok soveshchaniia po reforme mestnago samoupravleniia i upravleniia obrazovannago pri Ministerstve Vnutrennikh Del" (Folder 5-17)
  - Russia (Territory under White Armies, 1918-1920) Vremennoe Rossiiskoe Pravitel'stvo (Kolchak). Declaration, 1919 April (Box 11., Folder 1)
  - Russian Liberation Committee
    - General. Background information (Folder 2)
    - Bulletins, 1919 March-August (Folder 3)
    - Information leaflets (Folder 4)
  - Russskii Kruzhok v Londone. Miscellany (Folder 5)